<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Hugo - Tag - NetDevOps</title><link>https://netdevops.me/tags/hugo/</link><description>Hugo - Tag - NetDevOps</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://netdevops.me/tags/hugo/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to add YAML highlight in Highlight.js?</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2017/how-to-add-yaml-highlight-in-highlight.js/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2017/how-to-add-yaml-highlight-in-highlight.js/</guid><description>Haters gonna hate YAML, thats for sure. I am on the other hand in love with YAML; when one have to manually write/append config files I find YAML easier than JSON (and you have comments too).
Ansible, various static-site-generators and quite a lot of opensource tools use YAML syntax for the configuration purposes.
But still, YAML syntax highlighting is not a part of the Common languages shipped with highlight.js compiled package.</description></item><item><title>Setting up a Hugo blog with GitLab and CloudFlare</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2017/setting-up-a-hugo-blog-with-gitlab-and-cloudflare/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2017/setting-up-a-hugo-blog-with-gitlab-and-cloudflare/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://gohugo.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Hugo</a> gets a lot of <a href="https://www.staticgen.com/hugo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">attention</a> these days, it is basically snapping at the Jekyll' heels which is still the king of the hill! I don&rsquo;t know if Hugo' popularity coupled with <strong>the fastest static-site-generator</strong> statement, but for me &ldquo;speed&rdquo; is not the issue at all. A personal blog normally has few hundreds posts, not even close to thousands to be worried about slowness.</p>
<p>Then if it is not for speed then why did I choose Hugo? Because it became a solid product with a crowded community and all the common features available. <em>(To be honest I also got an illusion that one day I might start sharpen my Go skills through Hugo as well)</em>.</p>
<p>As you already noticed, this blog is powered by <strong>Hugo</strong>, is running on <strong>GitLab pages</strong>, with SSL certificate from <strong>CloudFlare</strong> and costs me <strong>$0</strong>. And I would like to write down the key pieces that&rsquo;ll probably be of help on your path to a zero-cost personal blog/cv/landing/etc.</p>]]></description></item></channel></rss>