<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Certification - Tag - NetDevOps</title><link>https://netdevops.me/tags/certification/</link><description>Certification - Tag - NetDevOps</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://netdevops.me/tags/certification/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Prepping up for and passing the Certified Openstack Administrator Exam</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2018/prepping-up-for-and-passing-the-certified-openstack-administrator-exam/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2018/prepping-up-for-and-passing-the-certified-openstack-administrator-exam/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Shortly after I passed <a href="/2018/prepping-up-for-and-passing-the-aws-certified-solution-architect-associate/" rel="">AWS CSA</a> exam I went on a hunt for the next certification to claim. Decided to tackle the <a href="https://www.openstack.org/coa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">Openstack COA</a> certification first saving the Docker/Kubernetes certification for a later occasion.</p>
<p>There is a common joke floating around: <em>&ldquo;Oh, is Openstack still a thing?&quot;</em> - yes, its pretty much still a thing, especially in the Telecom area where VMs are the only viable option for the most of the cases (think VNFs).<br>
Openstack also powers our teams public SDN lab - <a href="https://nuagex.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">NuageX</a> - that allows to provision a fully functional Nuage environment in a matter of minutes. So I wanted to get a better operational knowledge of Openstack to be able to support and tune the platform if necessary.</p>
<p>Disclaimer: I took the recently updated COA exam which is based on the Openstack Pike release, although I did not face any Pike-specific questions during the exam. This does not mean that the exam content will stay the same throughout the course evolution, so watch out for the updates.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>Prepping up for and passing the AWS Certified Solution Architect - Associate</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2018/prepping-up-for-and-passing-the-aws-certified-solution-architect-associate/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2018/prepping-up-for-and-passing-the-aws-certified-solution-architect-associate/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>On May 11th I passed the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/certification/certified-solutions-architect-associate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">AWS Certified Solution Architect Associate</a> exam which was harder then I expected. In this memo I will outline how I prepared to this exam, what topics you better pay more attention to and some tips and hints I could give to anyone going for AWS CSA exam.</p>
<p>Disclaimer: I took the original AWS CSA exam, not the one that was launched in Feb 2018; this older version is only available to schedule till August 2018. After that date the newer version of this exam will be the only one available. Watch out, it <a href="https://d1.awsstatic.com/training-and-certification/docs-sa-assoc/AWS_Certified_Solutions_Architect_Associate_Feb_2018_%20Exam_Guide_v1.5.2.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">has a new set of objectives</a>.</p>]]></description></item></channel></rss>