<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>gnmi - Tag - NetDevOps</title><link>https://netdevops.me/tags/gnmi/</link><description>gnmi - Tag - NetDevOps</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 06:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://netdevops.me/tags/gnmi/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Decoding gNMI with Wireshark</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2022/decoding-gnmi-with-wireshark/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2022/decoding-gnmi-with-wireshark/</guid><description>Okay, here goes my first attempt fitting the shoes of a content creator.
Please welcome the NetRel episode 001 - Decoding gNMI with Wireshark, it is a 35min journey of using Wireshark to parse the gNMI traffic (both non-secured and secured).
I won&amp;rsquo;t spend your time explaining the first episode; instead, let me tell you what I want the NetRel series to be about. I am interested in covering the aspects of network automation that are not widely covered.</description></item><item><title>gNMIc got better with YANG-completions</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmic-got-better-with-yang-completions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmic-got-better-with-yang-completions/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://gnmic.kmrd.dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><code>gnmic</code></a> was the first opensource project that I&rsquo;ve been part of that got widely adopted. As the maintainers of a public project, Karim and I were wondering when would we get the first external contribution.</p>
<p>To our surprise, the very <a href="https://github.com/karimra/gnmic/pull/136" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">first external contribution</a> laid out the foundation to one of the most exciting features of <code>gnmic</code> - YANG-Completions.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>Arista vEOS gNMI Tutorial</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2020/arista-veos-gnmi-tutorial/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2020/arista-veos-gnmi-tutorial/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>We were pleasantly surprised by the way community appreciated <a href="https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmic-gnmi-cli-client-and-collector/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">gNMIc</a> release. Thank you 🙏! That solidifies the fact that a well-formed, documented and easy to use gNMI tool was needed.</p>
<p>Now with gNMIc available to everybody its easy like never before to test gNMI implementation of different routing OSes. And in this post we will get our hands on <strong>Arista vEOS</strong>.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>gNMIc - gNMI CLI client and collector</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmic-gnmi-cli-client-and-collector/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmic-gnmi-cli-client-and-collector/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Despite the fact that <a href="https://github.com/openconfig/reference/blob/master/rpc/gnmi/gnmi-specification.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">gNMI</a> is defacto the go-to interface for a model-driven telemetry collection, we, as a community, had no gNMI tool that was easy to install, pleasure to use, documented and pre-built for common platforms. Until now.</p>
<p>I am excited to announce the public release of <a href="https://gnmic.kmrd.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><code>gnmic</code></a> - a CLI client and a collector that talks gNMI to your devices.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>gNMI Map</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmi-map/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2020/gnmi-map/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Lately I&rsquo;ve been involved in project that required quite a deep understanding of OpenConfig gRPC Network Management Interface (gNMI). Going over the <a href="https://github.com/openconfig/reference/blob/master/rpc/gnmi/gnmi-specification.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer">gNMI specification</a> multiple times made me realize that I can&rsquo;t fully build a mental map of all the messages and encapsulations without having a visual representation of it. So I&rsquo;ve made one, lets see what it has to offer.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>Easily exposing your local resources with ngrok and fwd</title><link>https://netdevops.me/2020/easily-exposing-your-local-resources-with-ngrok-and-fwd/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Author</author><guid>https://netdevops.me/2020/easily-exposing-your-local-resources-with-ngrok-and-fwd/</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>I bet every one of you was in a situation when you bloody needed to expose some local resource over internet. Letting a remote colleague to look at your work, delivering a demo being off-VPN, or any other reason to have your service be reachable over Internet.</p>
<p>And it was never easy; corporate firewalls stand on-guard ensuring you can&rsquo;t be agile and productive 😉</p>
<p>In this post I&rsquo;ll share with you how I glue <a href="https://ngrok.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><code>ngrok</code></a> and <a href="https://github.com/kintoandar/fwd" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer"><code>fwd</code></a> tools together to make my routers management interfaces exposed over Internet in a few clicks for free.</p>]]></description></item></channel></rss>